Guide to the Rose Weiner Photographs ALBA.PHOTO.116
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Rose Weiner Photographs
1920-1995
ALBA.PHOTO.116
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
0.25 linear feet (1 box)
Rose Weiner (1908-1995) was a nurse with the American Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy in Spain (AMB) during the Spanish Civil War. The images in this collection were collected by Weiner in a family scrapbook. The collection includes images of Weiner’s family and friends, AMB volunteers, and the daily life of soldiers in the Spanish Civil War.
Weiner, Rose
Provenance
The Rose Weiner Photograph Collection was separated from a scrapbook donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives by Gerrie Karasik in 1996. This scrapbook collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University. Manuscript material from the scrapbook can be found in the Rose Weiner Papers, ALBA #116.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Rose Weiner grew up in New York and attended the Montefiore Hospital School of Nursing from 1929-1932. She volunteered as a nurse with the American Medical Bureau of the North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy (AMB) during the Spanish Civil War. Weiner sailed for Spain in March 1937 and was first assigned as a floor nurse with a 200-bed convalescent hospital. After five months, she was given full charge of nursing at the medical unit. Weiner also spent several months on the front lines with a Mobile Hospital Unit followed by another assignment in charge of a 200-bed surgical hospital, followed by a stint as chief nurse in a 1500-bed surgical and medical hospital in her last six months. When she returned from Spain she was chief nurse at the Montefiore Hospital and a public health nurse in the New York Public School System.
Scope and Content Note
The Weiner Photo Collection consists predominantly of photographs related Weiner’s family life. The collection contains photographs from Weiner’s scrapbook including images of her childhood, family, and as a student at Montefiore Hospital School of Nursing. There is one image of Weiner’s father in the United States prior to the family’s arrival, one image of mother Eva Rubenstein with Rose, Dora, Milton, Sam and Florence in Lyubar, Russia and one image of the Weiner’s neighbors and cousins visiting the grave of Alexi Weiner, who was killed in a pogrom. Additional photographs document the AMB’s work in Spain during the Civil War including images of Jaime de Guzman, Captain T. Blin, unidentified medical personnel and an ambulance, in addition to images of unidentified soldiers. The photographs were removed from Weiner’s personal scrapbook and filed according to subject category. Detailed captions that accompanied some images in the scrapbook have been filed with the photographs. A photocopy of Weiner’s scrapbook, illustrating the original arrangement of the photographs, is contained in folder 23.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by topic.
The photographic prints are identified by four numbers separated by colons. The first number refers to the collection number, the second to the box number, the third to the folder number, and the fourth to the individual print. For example, the first print in this collection is labeled 116:1:1:1.
Organized into 1 series, photographs.
Photographs
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Rose Weiner Papers, ALBA 116
Medical Bureau and North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy.; Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy.; North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy.; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion.; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV.; Weiner, Rose; Photographs.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Pictorial works.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Hospitals.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Participation, American.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Women.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939.
- Series I: Photographs
  - American Medical Bureau (AMB): [Nurse?], ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Behind the Lines: Daily Life of the Soldiers, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Behind the Lines: Rest and Relaxation, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Blin, T: Captain, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - de Guzman, Jaime: AMB, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Group Portraits: Identified (Bill Gandall, [?] Raymond, Evelyn Raymond, Rose Klein), Benacasim, Oct 26, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Group Portraits: Unidentified, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Medical Vehicles, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Shipboard: Larry [?], Canadian, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Spanish Military Hospital [?], ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Wall Newspaper, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Weiner, Rose: AMB, Groups and Solo (Includes Lenora Temple, Mathilda Jankovic, Dulcea Hernaiz, John Jacob Posner, Rebecca Shulman, Evelyn Rahman, Epiphanio Lopez [?], Jose Gonzalez [?], Martha Mitchell, George Moser [?], Victor Hirschfield [?]), ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Weiner, Rose: Demonstrations/Marches (outside Spain), undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Weiner, Rose: Family and Friends, 1920-1954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Weiner, Rose: Holidays, 1991-1995 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Weiner, Rose: Montefiore Hospital, 1932-1940 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Weiner, Rose: Montefiore Hospital School of Nursing, 1929-1932 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Weiner, Rose: New York City Department of Health, Public Health Nurse Card, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Weiner, Rose: Trips/Vacations, 1957-1961 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Weiner, Rose: Weddings (Family and Friends), 1954, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Weiner, Rose: Youth, 1920s-1930s (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Weiner, Rose: Photocopy of Personal Scrapbook, 1920s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 22)